CHAPTER 10 DICKON The sun shone down for nearly a week on the secret garden. The Secret
Garden was what Mary called it when she was thinking of it. She liked the name,
and she liked still more the feeling that when its beautiful old walls shut
her in no one knew where she was. It seemed almost like being shut out of the
world in some fairy place. The few book she had read and liked had been fairy
story books, and she had read of secret gardens in some of the
stories. Sometimes people went to sleep in them for a hundred years, which she
had thought must be rather stupid. She had no intention of going to sleep, and,
in fact, she was becoming wider awake every day which passed at
mle She was beginning to like to be out of doors; she no longer hated the wind,
but enjoyed it. She could run faster, and longer, and she could skip up to a
100 The bulbs in the secret garden must have been much astonished. Such nice clear places were
made around them that they had all the breathing space they wanted, and really,
if Mistress Mary had known it, they began to cheer up under the dark earth and work
tremendously. The sun could get at them and warm them, and when the rain came
down it could reach them at once, so they began to feel very much
alive. Mary was an odd, determined little person, and now she had something
interesting to be determined about, she was very much absorbed, indeed. She worked
and dug and pulled up weeds steadily, only becoming more pleased with her work
every hour instead of tiring of it. It seemed to her like a fascinating sort of
play. She found any more of the sprouting pale green points than she had ever hoped to
find. They seemed to be starting up everywhere and each day she was sure she
found tiny new ones, some so tiny that they barely peeped above the earth. There
were so many that she remembered what Martha had said about the snow drops by the
thousands," and about bulbs spreading and making new ones. These had been left to
themselves for 10 years and perhaps they had spread, like the snow drops into
thousands. She wondered how long it would be before they showed that they were
flowers. Sometimes she stopped digging to look at the garden and try to imagine
what it would be like when it was covered with thousands of lovely things in
bloom. During that week of sunshine, she became more intimate with Ben weather
staff She surprised him several times by seeming to start up beside him as if she
sprang out of the earth. The truth was that she was afraid
that he would pick up his tools and go away if he saw her coming, so she always
walked toward him as silently as possible. But, in fact, he did not object
to her as strongly as he had at first. Perhaps he was secretly rather
flattered by her evident desire for his elderly company. Then, also, she was more civil
than she had been. He did not know that when she first saw him she spoke to him
as she would have spoken to a native, and had not known that a cross, sturdy old
Yorkshire man was not accustomed to Salam to his masters, and be merely commanded by them to do
things that like the robin," he said to her one morning when he lifted his head
and saw her standing by him. "I never knows when I shall see the or which side
they'll come from." "He's friends with me now," said Mary. "That's like him," snapped Ben
Weatherstaff making up to the women folk just for vanity and
flightiness. There's nothing he wouldn't do for the sake of showing off and
flirting his tail feathers He's as full of pride as an eggs full of
meat." He very seldom talked much and sometimes did not even answer Mary's
questions except by a grunt, but but this morning he said more than usual. He stood
up and rested one hob nailed boot on the top of his spade while he looked her
over. "How long has thou been here?" he jerked out. "I think it's about a month," she
answered that's beginning to do mistle credit," he said that's a bit fatter than
th was and that's not quite so yellow they looked like a young plucked crow
when they first came into this garden.
Thinks s to myself I never set eyes on an uglier sour-faced
young Mary was not vain and as she had never thought much of her looks she was
not greatly disturbed. "I know I'm fatter," she said. "My
stockings are getting tighter. They used to make wrinkles. There's the robin, Ben weather
staff There, indeed, was the robin, and she thought he looked nicer than ever. His
red waste coat was as glossy as satin and he flirted his wings and tail and
tilted his head and hopped about with all sorts of lively graces. He seemed
determined to make Ben weather staff admire him. But Ben was
sarcastic I there that art!" he said th can put up with me for a bit sometimes
when that's got no one better that's been reading up thy waste coat and
polishing thy feathers this two weeks. I know what th's up to th caught in some
bold young madam somewhere telling thy lies to her about being the finest
robin on Mile Moore and ready to fight all the rest of them Oh! look at him!" exclaimed
Mary. The robin was evidently in a fascinating, bold mood. He hopped closer
and closer and looked at Ben Weatherstaff more and more engagingly. He flew on to the nearest
current bush and tilted his head and sang a little song right at him thou
thinks thou get over me by doing that," said Ben, wrinkling his face up in such a
way that Mary felt sure he was trying not to look
pleased thou thinks no one can stand out against thee— —that's what the thinks." The
robin spread his wings— —Mary could scarcely believe her eyes. He flew right
up to the handle of Ben weather staff's spade and a lighted on the top of it.
Then the old man's face wrinkled itself slowly into a new expression. He stood
still as if he were afraid to breathe— —as if he would not have stirred for the
world, lest his robin should start away.
He spoke quite in a whisper. "Well, I'm danged!" he said as
softly as if he were saying something quite different th does know how to get at a
chap th does TH fair unearthly th so KN And he stood without stirring— —almost
without drawing his breath— —until the robin gave another flirt to his wings and flew
away. Then he stood looking at the handle of the spade as if there might be Magic
in it, and then he began to dig again and said nothing for several minutes. But
because he kept breaking into a slow grin now and then, Mary was not afraid to
talk to him. "Have you a garden of your own?" she asked.
"No. I'm Bachelor and lodge with Martin at the gate." "If you had one," said Mary, "what would
you plant?" "Cabbages and potatoes and onions." "But if you wanted to make a
flower garden," persisted Mary, "what would you plant?" "Bulbs and sweet smelling things—
—but mostly roses." Mary's face lighted up. "Do you like
roses?" she said. Ben weather staff rooted up a weed and threw it aside before he
answered. "Well, yes, I do. I was learned that by a young lady I was gardener to.
She had a lot in a place she was fond of and she loved them like they was
children— —or robins. I've seen her bend over and kiss him He dragged out another weed and
scowled at it. "That were as much as 10 year' ago." "Where is she now?" asked Mary, much
interested interested. "Heaven," he answered, and drove his spade deep into the soil
according to what parson says." "What happened to the roses?" Mary
asked again, more interested than ever. "They was left to themselves." Mary
was becoming quite excited. "Did they quite die? Do roses quite die when they
are left to themselves?" she ventured. "Well, I'd got to like them and I liked her and
she liked them Ben weather staff admitted reluctantly. "Once or twice a year I'd go
and work at them a bit— —prune them and dig about the roots. They run wild, but
they was in rich soil, so some of them lived." "When they have no leaves and look
gray and brown and dry, how can you tell whether they are dead or alive?" inquired
Mary. "Wait till the spring gets at him wait till the sun shines on the rain and
the rain falls on the sunshine and then they'll find
out." "How— —how?" cried Mary, forgetting to be careful. "Look along the twigs and
branches and if th sees a bit of a brown lump swelling here and there, watch it
after the warm rain and see what happens."
He stopped suddenly and looked curiously at her eager face. "Why does that care so
much about roses and such, all of a sudden?" he demanded. Mistress Mary felt her face
grow red. She was almost afraid to answer. "I— —I want to play that— —that I have
a garden of my own," she stammered. "I— —there is nothing for me to do. I have nothing—
—and no one." "Well," said Ben Weatherstaff slowly, as he watched her, "that's true there
hasn't." He said it in such an odd way that Mary wondered if he was actually a
little sorry for her. She had never felt sorry for herself; she had only felt
tired and cross, because she disliked people and things so much. But now the
world seemed to be changing and getting nicer. If no one found out about the
secret garden, she should enjoy herself always. She stayed with him for 10 or 15
minutes longer and asked him as many questions as she dared. He answered every
one of them in his queer grunting way and he did not seem really cross and did
not pick up his spade and leave her. He said something about roses just as she
was going away and it reminded her of the ones he had said he had been fond
of. "Do you go and see those other roses now?" she asked. "Not been this year. My
rheumatics has made me too stiff in the joints." He said it in his grumbling voice,
and then quite suddenly he seemed to get angry with her, though she did not see
why he should. "Now look here!" he said sharply. "Don't that ask so many questions
that the worst wench for asking questions I've ever come across. Get thee
gone and play thee. I've done talking for today And he said it so crossly that she
knew there was not the least use in staying another minute. She went skipping slowly down the
outside walk, thinking him over and saying to herself that query as it was,
here was another person whom she liked in spite of his crossness. She liked old Ben weather
staff Yes, she did like him. She always wanted to try to make him talk to her.
Also she began to believe that he knew everything in the world about
flowers. There was a laurel hedged walk which curved around the secret garden
and ended at a gate which opened into a wood, in the
park. She thought she would skip around this walk and look into the wood and see
if there were any rabbits hopping about.
She enjoyed the skipping very much and when she reached the little gate she
opened it and went through because she heard a low, peculiar whistling sound and
wanted to find out what it was. It was a very strange thing
indeed. She quite caught her breath as she stopped to to look at it. A boy was
sitting under a tree, with his back against it, playing on a rough wooden
pipe. He was a funny looking boy about 12 He looked very clean and his nose
turned up and his cheeks were as red as poppies and never had Mistress Mary seen
such round and such blue eyes in any boy's face. And on the trunk of the tree he
leaned against, a brown squirrel was singing and watching him, and from behind
a bush nearby a pheasant was delicately stretching his neck to peep
out, and quite near him were two rabbits sitting up and sniffing with tremulous
noses— —and actually it appeared as if they were all drawing near to watch him
and listen to the strange low little call his pipe seemed to
make. When he saw Mary he held up his hand and spoke to her in a voice almost
as low as and rather like his piping.
"Don't thou move," he said it flym Mary remained motionless. He stopped playing his pipe
and began to rise from the ground. He moved so slowly that it scarcely seemed
as though he were moving at all, but at last he stood on his feet and then the
squirrel scampered back up into the branches of his tree, the pheasant
withdrew his head and the rabbits dropped on all fours and began to hop
away, though not at all as if they were frightened. "I'm Dickon," the boy said. "I
know that Miss Mary." Then Mary realized that somehow she had known at first that he was
Dickon. Who else could have been charming rabbits and pheasants as the natives
charm snakes in India? He had a wide, red, curving mouth and his smile spread all
over his face. "I got up slow," he explained, "because if thou makes a quick move it
startles him A body has to move gentle and speak low when wild things is
about." He did not speak to her as if they had never seen each other before but as
if he knew her quite well. Mary knew nothing about boys and
she spoke to him a little stiffly because she felt rather
shy. "Did you get Martha's letter?" she asked. He nodded his curly Rus colored
head. "That's why I come." He stooped to pick up something which had been lying
on the ground beside him when he piped. "I've got the garden tools. There's
a little spade and rake and a fork and ho ah they are goodin There's a Trel too
and the woman in the shop threw in a packet of white poppy and one of blue
lar spur when I bought the other seeds." "Will you show the seeds to me?" Mary
said. She wished she could talk as he did.
His speech was so quick and easy. It sounded as if he liked her and was not
the least afraid she would not like him, though he was only a common more boy, in
patched clothes and with a funny face and a rough Rusty red
head. As she came closer to him she noticed that there was a clean fresh
scent of heather and grass and leaves about him, almost as if he were made of
them. She liked it very much and when she looked into his funny face
with the red cheeks and round blue eyes she forgot that she had felt
shy. "Let us sit down on this log and look at them," she
said. They sat down and he took a clumsy little brown paper package out of his
coat pocket. He untied the string and inside there were ever so many neater
and smaller packages with a picture of a flower on each
one. "There's a lot of Minette and poppies," he said Minion's the sweetest smelling
thing as grows and it'll grow wherever you cast it, same as poppies will thems
will come up and bloom if you just whistle to them them's the nicest of all."
He stopped and turned his head quickly, his poppy cheeked face lighting up.
"Where's that robin as is calling us?" he said. The chirp came from a thick holly
bush, bright with scarlet berries, and Mary thought she knew whose it
was. "Is it really calling us?" she asked I said Dickon, as if it was the most
natural thing in the world, "he's calling someone he's friends with that same is
saying Here I am. Look at me. I wants a
bit of a chat.' There he is in the bush
who is he?" "He's Ben weather staffs but I think he knows me a little," answered Mary
I he knows thee," said Dickon in his low voice again
and he likes thee. He's took thee on.
He'll tell me all about thee in a minute." He moved quite close to the bush
with the slow movement Mary had noticed before, and then he made a sound almost
like the robin's own twitter. The robin listened a few seconds,
intently, and then answered quite as if he were replying to a
question ah heun's a friend of yours," chuckled Dickon. "Do you you think he is?" cried Mary
eagerly. She did so want to know. "Do you think he really likes
me?" "He wouldn't come near thee if he didn't," answered Dickon. "Birds is rare
choosers and a robin can flout a body worse than a man. See, he's making up to
thee now. 'Cannot thou see a chap?' he's saying And it really seemed as if it
must be true. He so sidled and twittered and tilted as he hopped on his bush. "Do
you understand everything birds say?" said Mary dickens's grin spread until he
seemed all wide, red, curving mouth, and he rubbed his rough
head. "I think I do, and they think I do," he
said. "I've lived on the moall with them so long. I've watched them break shell
and come out and fledge and learn to fly and begin to sing, till I think I'm one
of them Sometimes I think perhaps I'm a bird, or
a fox, or a rabbit, or a squirrel, or even a beetle and I don't know
it." He laughed and came back to the log and began to talk about the flower seeds
again. He told her what they looked like when they were flowers; he told her how
to plant them, and watch them, and feed and water them. "See here," he said suddenly,
turning round to look at her. "I'll plant them for thee myself. Where is the garden?"
Mary's thin hands clutched each other as they lay on her lap. She did not know
what to say, so for a whole minute she said nothing. She had never thought of
this. She felt miserable. And she felt as if she went red and then
pale that's got a bit of garden, hasn't that Dickens said. It was true that she
had turned red and then pale Dickens saw her do it, and as she still said nothing,
he began to be puzzled. "Wouldn't they give thee a bit?" he
asked. "Hasn't thou got any yet?" She held her hands even tighter and turned her eyes toward
him. "I don't know anything about boys," she said slowly. "Could you keep a secret, if I told
you one? It's a great secret. I don't know what I should do if anyone found it out.
I believe I should die!" She said the last sentence quite fiercely. Dickon looked
more puzzled than ever and even rubbed his hand over his rough head again, but
he answered quite good humoredly I'm keeping secrets all the time," he said. "If
I couldn't keep secrets from the other lads, secrets about Fox's cubs and birds'
nests and wild things' holes, there'd be not safe on the mo I I can keep
secrets." Mistress Mary did not mean to put out her hand and clutch his sleeve
but she did it.
"I've stolen a garden," she said very fast.
"It isn't mine. It isn't anybody's. Nobody wants it, nobody cares for it, nobody ever
goes into it. Perhaps everything is dead in it already; I don't know." She began to
feel hot and as contrary as she had ever felt in her life. "I don't care, I don't
care! Nobody has any right to take it from me when I care about it and they don't.
They're letting it die, all shut in by itself," she ended passionately, and she
threw her arms over her face and burst out crying— —poor little Mistress Mary
dickens's curious blue eyes grew rounder and rounder uh he said, drawing his
exclamation out slowly, and the way he did it meant both wonder and
sympathy I have nothing to do," said Mary.
"Nothing belong belongs to me. I found it myself and I got into it myself. I was
only just like the robin, and they wouldn't take it from the
robin." "Where is it?" asked Dickon in a dropped voice. Mistress Mary got up from
the log at once. She knew she felt contrary again, and obstinate, and she did
not care at all. She was imperious and Indian, and at the same time hot and
sorrowful. "Come with me and I'll show you," she said. She led him round the laurel
path and to the walk where the ivy grew so thickly. Dickon followed her with a queer,
almost pitying, look on his face. He felt as if he were being led to
look at some strange bird's nest and must move softly. When she stepped to the wall and
lifted the hanging ivy he started. There was a door and Mary pushed
it slowly open and they passed loed in together, and then Mary stood and waved her hand round
defiantly. "It's this," she said. "It's a secret garden, and I'm the only one in
the world who wants it to be alive."
Dickon looked round and round about it, and round and round
again e he almost whispered, "it is a queer, pretty place! It's like as if a
body was in a dream